Eldri Dieson Papers, 1928-1986, n.d.
Sophia Smith Collection
Eldri Dieson Papers
1928-1986, n.d.
Dieson, Eldri, 1905-1984
MS 602
5 boxes (2.5 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
YWCA executive and overseas official. The Eldri Dieson Papers consist of one linear foot of biographical materials, correspondence, diaries, memorabilia, newspaper clippings, photographs, research notes, and scrapbooks primarily related to Dieson's work for the YWCA of the U.S.A. The bulk of the papers focus on Dieson's work for the YWCA's Foreign Division in Japan and in Chile.
Biographical Note
Eldri Louise Dieson was born March 31, 1905, in Dell Rapids, South Dakota. After earning a B.A. from St. Olaf College in 1927, Dieson briefly studied sociology at the University of Minnesota and worked for the Lutheran Welfare Association in Minneapolis before joining the staff of the YWCA.
In the summer of 1927 Dieson participated in the YWCA National Student Council's Students in Industry Project, known as "a summer course in reality." College graduates spent six weeks working in factories "as part of an experiment and to gain first hand information for social work."
Between 1927 and 1942 Dieson worked as an Industrial or Business and Industry Secretary in YWCAs in Minneapolis, Minnesota (1927-30, 1936-42); Canton, Ohio (1930-32); and Allentown, Pennsylvania (1932). Dieson attended the New School of Social Work in 1935-36.
During World War II Dieson moved to the national YWCA staff, working in the Community Division in the fall of 1942, then becoming an Industrial Secretary, 1943-48. During the summer of 1944 she worked in Maine with the Women's Emergency Farm Service of the Women's Land Army.
After the war Dieson moved to the staff of the Foreign Division as a Program Consultant in Japan from 1948 to 1951. On her return to the U.S., she joined the staff of the United Community Defense Services staff of the YWCA helping new residents in rapidly growing cities and towns adjacent to defense industries. The aim of this work was to fill gaps in services for a relatively brief period until the cities and towns were able to do so.
In 1955 Dieson went to the YWCA of Chile. She returned to the States in 1960 to help develop YWCA's Latin America United States Exchange Project. The Project provided opportunities for women from YWCAs in Argentina, Bolivia, Brazil, Chile, Mexico, Puerto Rico, Uruguay, and the United States to share inter-American concerns and resources. In 1960 she received St. Olaf College's Distinguished Alumni Award.
Dieson went back to Chile the following year as director of the Latin America United States Exchange Project. From 1962 she also worked closely with the YWCA-Peace Corps project in community development in Valparaiso and Santiago.
In the fall of 1965 Dieson took the post of Field Consultant for the Southern Region for the YWCA of the U.S.A. In this capacity she advised YWCAs in thirteen southern states on all aspects of program and administration. Dieson retired from the YWCA circa 1971.
Eldri Dieson died in Hennepin, Minnesota in 1994.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Eldri Dieson Papers consist of 4 linear feet of biographical materials, correspondence, diaries, memorabilia, newspaper clippings, photographs, research notes, and scrapbooks primarily related to Dieson's work for the YWCA of the U.S.A. The bulk of the papers date from 1948 to 1964 and focus on Dieson's work for the YWCA's Foreign Division in Japan and in Chile. A small portion of the contents are in Japanese and Spanish.
Organization of the Collection
This collection is organized into three series:
BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS AND CORRESPONDENCE
ORGANIZATIONS
PHOTOGRAPHS
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection without any additional restrictions.
The Eldri Dieson Papers came to the Sophia Smith Collection with the Records of the YWCA of the U.S.A. in 2002. The YWCA received them from Dieson's niece Tonia Jauch in 1993.
Dieson, Eldri, 1905-1984; Japan -- History -- 20th century -- Sources; Peace Corps (U.S.) -- Chile -- History; United Community Defense Services; Young Women's Christian Associations -- Chile -- History; Young Women's Christian Associations -- Japan -- History; Young Women's Christian Association of the U.S.A. -- History
Related materials are in the YWCA of the U.S.A. Records
A scrapbook created by Eldri Dieson during her college years is housed in the St. Olaf College Archives, Northfield, Minnesota.
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS AND CORRESPONDENCE
  This series contains a small amount of general biographical information plus letters Dieson wrote home to her family from YWCA postings in Japan, Kentucky, and Chile, 1948-64. Also included is Dieson's Guest Book which traveled with her from Japan to the United States to Chile and back to the U.S
- SERIES II. ORGANIZATIONS
  This series contains diaries, printed materials, memorabilia, newspaper clippings, research notes, and scrapbooks from Dieson's work for the Women's Land Army, the YWCA of the U.S.A., and YWCA/United Community Defense Services. There is a detailed scrapbook about the 1928 National Student Council's Student in Industry Project among these materials.
- SERIES III. PHOTOGRAPHS
  This series makes up more than half of the total bulk of the Papers. It consists of photographic prints, negatives, and slides of Dieson's work and travels in Asia and South America; and of various YWCA activities in the United States.
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS AND CORRESPONDENCE
  - General 1932-85, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence to family 1948-64, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
  - Guest book [mostly Japan] 1951-86 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- SERIES II. ORGANIZATIONS
  - Women's Land Army: Women's Emergency Farm Service of Maine 1944 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - YWCA of the U.S.A.
    - Students in Industry National Student Council Summer Project
      - Scrapbook 1928-29 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Round robin letters by 1928 participantsDec 1930 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Foreign Division, Japan
      - General 1948-51, 1986, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Correspondence from Hisae [S.?] 1950 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Diaries 1948-50 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - "Religious and Historical Background of Japan" by Shizu Nakajo, lecture for the World Fellowship Committee of the Tokyo YWCAn.d. (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Scrapbook 1948-49 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - United Community Defense Service-YWCA Paducah, Kentucky: handbook 1951 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Foreign Division, Chile
      - General 1957-85, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 2-3)
      - YWCA-Peace Corps project 1963, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - YWCA Latin America-US Exchange Project 1961 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- SERIES III. PHOTOGRAPHS
  - Prints and negatives
    - Miscellaneous 1986, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - YWCA of Chile
      - Loose photographs and postcards 1955-65 (Box 2, Folder 7-10)
      - Album 1961 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - YWCA of Japan
      - Loose photographs and postcards 1985-88, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - Albums 1948-51, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 2-3)
    - YWCA of the U.S.A.
      - United Community Defense Services programs (Box 3)
        - Paducah, Kentucky 1953, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 4)
        - Piketon, Ohio 1954 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      - Conference, Dallas, Texasspring 1978 (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - Student Leadership Workshop, Learning Center XII 1981 (Box 3, Folder 7)
      - National Student Assemblyn.d. (Box 3, Folder 8)
      - Roundtable at Morgan State University or Howard Universityn.d. (Box 3, Folder 9)
      - Unidentified meeting at 600 Lexington Ave.n.d. (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Slides
    - Argentina: gauchos 1955-64 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Cambodia: Angkor Watn.d. (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Chile 1955-64 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Costa Rican.d. (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Jamaican.d. (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Japan 1948-51 (Box 4, Folder 6-8)
    - Thailand, Bankok (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Other countries 1951, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - United States
      - Paducah, Kentuckyn.d. (Box 4, Folder 11)
      - South Dakotan.d. (Box 4, Folder 12)
      - United Community Defense Services 1951 (Box 4, Folder 13)
      - Unidentified events 1955-69, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 14)